A Register of the John Somerville papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Somerville papers
1930-1995
95058
Somerville, John, 1905-
15 manuscript boxes (6.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, and notes, relating to Marxist philosophy, philosophy and education in the Soviet Union, peace and nuclear disarmament movements, and the loyalty-security program in the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American philosopher; president, Society for the Philosophical Study of Marxism; president, International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide.
1905 March 13 Born, New York City, New York
1935-1937 Somerville and his wife, Rose Maurer Somerville, work in the U.S.S.R. studying Soviet philosophy
1938 Receives Ph.D. in philosophy from Columbia University
1939-1967 At Hunter College (the City University of New York) Somerville advances from Instructor to Professor Emeritus
1946 Author, Soviet Philosophy: A Study of Theory and Practice
1949 Author, The Philosophy of Peace
1950s Testifies in three trials as an expert witness on the doctrines of Marxism-Leninism
1956 Author, The Communist Trials and the American Tradition
1962-1987 Founding editor and Editor in Chief of the translation quarterly, Soviet Studies in Philosophy (now Russian Studies in Philosophy)
1962 Co-founder of the Society for the Philosophical Study of Dialectical Materialism (later, the Society for the Philosophical Study of Marxism)
1963 August Helps organize first bi-national conference of American and Soviet philosophers at the XIIIth World Congress of Philosophy in Mexico City
1963 December 27 Organizes first full dialogue on U.S. soil between American and Soviet philosophers at the American Philosophical Association (APA) conference, in Washington D.C.
1967 Author, The Philosophy of Marxism
1967-1972 Taught at the United States International University
1975 Author, The Peace Revolution: Ethos and Social Process
1976 Author, The Crisis: The True Story of How the World Almost Ended (play)
1978 Co-founder of The Union of American and Japanese Professionals Against Nuclear Omnicide
1980 Initiates California Campaign for No-First-Use of Nuclear Weapons
1981 Awarded the degree Doctor of Humane Letters from Denison University; Author, Soviet Marxism and Nuclear War and The Last Inquest (play)
1983 Co-founder and first president of the International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide (IPPNO) at the XVIIth World Congress of Philosophy in Montreal
1984 Initiates National Campaign for a Policy of No-First-Use of Nuclear Weapons
1986 Organizes first conference of the IPPNO in St. Louis
1987 Receives Gandhi Peace Award from the board of directors of Promoting Enduring Peace
1987 Receives Bertrand Russell Peace Award
1994 January 8 Died, El Cajon, California
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 5 series: Biographical File, Diaries, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes materials related to Marxist philosophy, philosophy and education in the Soviet Union, peace and nuclear disarmament movements, and the loyalty-security program in the United States, in the form of correspondence, writings, and notes. The collection encompasses the years 1930-1995, with the bulk of the materials covering 1960-1989.
The bulk of the material relates generally to John Somerville's academic career, which encompassed the study of Marxism, Soviet philosophy, and education, as well as his political activism against the proliferation of nuclear weapons, nuclear war, and nuclear omnicide, a term coined by Somerville to describe the extinction of the human species as a result of human action. Most of these materials relate to his work as co-founder and president of the Society for the Philosophical Study of Marxism (SPSM), the International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide (IPPNO), and his support of and membership in related organizations such as the American Philosophical Association (APA) and The Union of American and Japanese Professionals Against Nuclear Omnicide (UAJPANO).
The original order of the materials was retained within each folder in the collection, as received by the Hoover Archives. The folders in the collection were organized into five series: Biographical File, Diaries, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings and Subject File. Researchers should be aware that the materials under a particular subject heading do not necessarily represent the entirety of that subject and more materials may be available in another series. Even though most of the materials in the collection are found in the correspondence series, because a substantial amount of printed matter other than correspondence is interfiled within the correspondence folders, a reasonable effort has been made to identify important materials within these folders that are not categorized as correspondence. Researchers looking for a specific writing, assuming it isn't in the speeches and writings series, should strongly consider browsing through the correspondence folders.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Society for the Philosophical Study of Marxism.; International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide.; Philosophy, Marxist.; Philosophy--Soviet Union.; Education--Soviet Union.; Peace.; Disarmament. .; Internal security--United States. .; Philosophers.
Related Collections
World without War Council records, 1948-2008, Hoover Institution Archives
Robert H. Kupperman papers, 1965-1995, Hoover Institution Archives
Fred Charles Iklé papers, 1972-1988, Hoover Institution Archives
Lorelei Kelly collection, 1983-1993, Hoover Institution Archives
Edward Teller papers, 1930-2003, Hoover Institution Archives
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1935-1994 (Box 1)
  Correspondence, clippings and other printed material; includes material relating to John Somerville's doctoral degree, academic and professional career, and condolences to his wife after his death. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence relating to Somerville's doctoral examination, 1935-1936 (Folder 1: 1)
    Some in Russian
  - Correspondence, recommendations, Hunter College, Columbia and Cornell University, 1935-1944 (Folder 1: 2)
  - One page biography, circa 1946 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings and interviews relating to John Somerville, 1949-1990 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Clippings, writings and transcript, 1950-1988 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Citation for the presentation of Doctor of Humane Letters from Denison University, with photograph, 1981 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Book reviews, 1973-1974 (Folder 1: 7)
    in German
  - Recommendations, 1973 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Clippings, press releases and essays by Somerville related to awards received by him, 1980-1987 (Folder 1: 9)
  - John Somerville's statement of retirement from the presidency of the International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide (IPPNO), correspondence, a biographical sketch An Appreciation: John Somerville, 1905-1994 and condolences to Rose Somerville after John Somerville's death, 1991-1994 (Folder 1: 10)
- Diaries, 1935-1939 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1935-1939 (Folder 1: 11-23)
    Diaries describe the period during and after which John and Rose Maurer Somerville lived in the U.S.S.R. studying and lecturing on Soviet philosophy and education. Arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence, 1940-1993 (Box 2-10)
  Letters, writings, reports, programs, memoranda, resolutions, newsletters, clippings, research material, pamphlets and miscellany. The bulk of this material relates generally to John Somerville's academic career in the study of Marxism, Soviet philosophy, education and his political activism against the proliferation of nuclear weapons and nuclear war, and his work as co-founder and president of the Society for the Philosophical Study of Marxism (SPSM) and the International Philosophers for the Prevention of Nuclear Omnicide (IPPNO). Arranged into two subseries: Chronological Correspondence and Alphabetical Correspondence.
  - Chronological correspondence, 1933-1993 (Folder 2-6)
    - 1933-1939 (Folder 2 :1)
    - 1940-1953 (Folder 2: 2-5)
      including a letter from Harold H. Fisher, director of the Hoover Institution, June 8, 1949, clippings, notes, and the Bulletin of the Committee on Education, National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Vol. I, No. 2, September-October 1945
    - 1947-1961 (Folder 2: 6-7)
      transcript
    - 1949-1990 (Folder 2: 8)
      meeting minutes
    - 1950-1959 (Folder 2: 9-10)
      writings
    - 1960-1967 (Folder 2: 11-12)
      Some in Russian, clippings
    - 1960-1969 (Folder 3: 1-4)
      writings, clippings
    - 1961-1993 (Folder 3: 5-8)
    - 1962-1968 (Folder 3: 9)
    - 1963-1968 (Folder 3: 10)
    - 1966-1992 (Folder 4: 1-2)
      some in Japanese
    - 1970-1980 (Folder 4: 3-8)
      writings, announcements, newsletters
    - 1979-1990 (Folder 4: 9-10)
    - 1980-1989 (Folder 5: 1-4)
      proposed APA resolution and "Rough Draft of a Proposal for Soviet-American Visits and Interaction (SAVI) Paul Allen, 11/22/88"
    - 1980-1990 (Folder 5: 5-9)
      clippings, statements, press releases, writings and the IPPNO Constitution "Approved at the Organizing Meeting Held at the XVIIth World Congress of Philosophy in Montreal, August 23, 1983"
    - 1980-1993 (Folder 5: 10)
      writings, resolutions
    - 1980-1993 (Folder 5: 11)
      book review
    - 1982-1992 (Folder 6: 1)
    - 1985-1991 (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1990-1992 (Folder 6: 3)
    - 1990-1992 (Folder 6: 4)
      relating to The Crisis and the IPPNO
  - Alphabetical correspondence, 1936-1944 (Folder 6-11)
    - Alpven, Hannes, 1978-1989 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Allen, Paul, 1982-1989 (Folder 6: 6)
    - American Philosophical Society (APA), 1966-1988 (Folder 6: 7)
    - American Philosophical Association, Committee on Freedom for Latin-American Philosophers, 1969-1972 (Folder 6: 8)
    - Blanshard, Brand, 1966-1967 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Bulgaria, clippings, writings, 1973-1986 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Bulgarian Philosophy Society, 1973-1986 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Burtt, Edwin Arthur, 1980-1987 (Folder 6: 12)
    - Catholic Bishops, clippings, 1967-1983 (Folder 6: 13)
    - Cohen, Robert S., 1962-1981 (Folder 6: 14)
    - The Crisis, reviews, writings, 1976-1992 (Folder 6: 15-17)
    - Daffern, Thomas, and Phipps, John-Francis, 1985-1989 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Dunham, Barrows, 1961-1992 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1950-1987 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Fédération Internationale des Societes de Philosophie (FISP), XVII World Congress of Philosophy, 1981-1993 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Frazier, Howard, Promoting Enduring Peace Inc., 1981-1993 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Fried, John H.E., 1979-1991 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Friedman, Howard, 1990-1993 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Ginsberg, Robert, 1972-1991 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Glossop, Ronald, 1985-1992 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Hampsch, George, IPPNO Newsletter, Spring 1989, Spring, 1989, 1976-1990 (Folder 7: 10)
    - Herg, Alice, 1954-1955 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Hirschbein, Ronald, 1972-1993 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Hunter College, clippings, statement, 1965-1992 (Folder 7: 13)
    - India, 1989-1991 (Folder 7: 14)
    - International Conference on the Holocaust and Genocide, Jerusalem and Tel Aviv, 1982, press releases, 1980-1983 and UAJPANO writings, pamphlets, 1980-1984 (Folder 7: 15)
    - International Directory of Philosophy and Philosophers, writings, 1964 (Folder 7: 16)
    - IPPNO, World Congress of Philosophy, XVII, Montreal, Canada, 1983, program, press release, 1980-1983 (Folder 8: 1)
    - IPPNO, meeting minutes, 1980-1986 (Folder 8: 2)
    - IPPNO, 1983-1989 (Folder 8: 3-4)
    - IPPNO and the United Nations, press releases, 1983-1991 (Folder 8: 5)
    - IPPNO Conference, St. Louis, 1986 (including Linus Pauling), program, press releases, 1985-1986 (Folder 8: 6)
    - IPPNO, World Congress of Philosophy, XVIII, Brighton, England, 1988, reports, program, 1985-1988 (Folder 8: 7)
    - IPPNO and CPP, writing, meeting minutes, 1985-1989 (Folder 8: 8)
    - IPPNO and the Concerned Philosophers for Peace (CPP), newsletters, 1985-1991 (Folder 8: 9)
    - IPPNO, Russia, 1986-1990 (Folder 8: 10)
    - IPPNO, 1986-1994 (Folder 8: 11)
    - IPPNO, Moscow, Russia conference, 1990, meeting minutes, 1987-1992 (Folder 9: 1)
    - India, 1968-1993 (Folder 9: 2)
    - International Philosophy Congress, XIII, Mexico City 1963, articles, 1962-1965 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Japan, clippings, writings, 1952-1991 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1966-1995 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Lown, Bernard, writings, 1981-1992 (Folder 9: 6)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1950-1955 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Mannerheim, Augustin, writing and Alfven, Hannes, press release, clipping, 1971-1995 (Folder 9: 8)
    - Marcuse, Herbert, 1972 (Folder 9: 9)
    - Masaryk Institute, 1948 (Folder 9: 10)
    - McGovern, George, writings, 1980 (Folder 9: 11)
    - Neurath, Holland, photo, 1936 (Folder 9: 12)
    - Nobel Peace Prize, 1981-1982 (Folder 9: 13)
    - Notables including: Sir Alfred Ayer, Fred Warner Neal, Lord Philip Noel-Baker, Cornelius Kruse, W.H. Ferry, William Wilson, J.W. Fulbright, Herbert Marcuse, Darwin J. Meserole, 1948-1992 (Folder 9: 14-16)
    - Parsons, Howard, 1961-1991 (Folder 9: 17)
    - Pauling, Linus, 1983-1992 (Folder 10: 1)
    - Publications, 1951-1963 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Polish Academy of Sciences, 1977-1987 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Progress publishers, 1971-1994 (Folder 10: 4-7)
    - Rasker, A.J., 1978-1984 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Riepe, Dale, 1971-1994 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Schaff, Adam, 1961-1992 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Schwartz, Gunther, 1970-1993 (Folder 10: 11)
    - Shibata, Shingo, 1984-1986 (Folder 10: 12)
    - Soviet philosophers, 1962-1977 (Folder 10: 13)
    - Soviet Studies in Philosophy, University of Glasgow, 1962-1967 (Folder 10: 14-16)
    - Soviet Studies in Philosophy, International Arts and Sciences Press, 1962-1986 (Folder 10: 17)
    - Thomas, Claire, clippings, 1983-1986 (Folder 10: 18)
    - Thompson, Edward, Palmer (E.P.), writings, clippings, 1981-1990 (Folder 10: 19)
    - Union of American and Japanese Professionals Against Nuclear Omnicide (UAJPANO), 1982-1989 (Folder 10: 20)
    - USSR, notes, 1947-1948 (Folder 10: 21)
    - USSR, and writings, 1947-1993 (Folder 11: 1)
    - USSR, Academy of Science, 1958 (Folder 11: 2)
    - USSR, and writings, clippings, 1961-1988 (Folder 11: 3-7)
    - World Congress of Philosophy, XVI, Düsseldorf, Germany, 1978, writings, 1976-1979 (Folder 11: 8)
      Some in German
    - World Congress of Philosophy, XVI, Vienna, Austria, 1968, writings, 1967-1968 (Folder 11: 9)
    - World Congress of Sociology, VII, Varna, Bulgaria, 1970, clippings, writings, photos, 1969-1970 (Folder 11: 10-11)
    - Yugoslavia, 1961-1986 (Folder 11: 12-13)
- Speeches and Writings, 1935-1990 (Box 11-13)
  Typescript and printed copies, notes, reviews, correspondence, and transcripts. Arranged chronologically. See also Subject File for reviews
  - Notebook, 1935-1936 (Folder 11: 14)
  - Interviews with Professors Rudas, Broushlinski, and Razumovsky, Moscow, 1936-1937 (Folder 11: 15)
  - Letters to the editor, clippings, 1936-1937 (Folder 11: 16)
  - Articles, relating to Afghanistan, Marxism, Catholic Bishops, Cuban Missiles, Nuclear Weapons, and Omnicide, 1949-1989 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Letters to the editor, clippings, 1950-1989 (Folder 12: 2-3)
  - Articles about Albert Einstein, Elie Wiesel, Soviet philosophy, 1956-1986 (Folder 12: 4)
  - Lectures, Moscow, 1958 (Folder 12: 5-8)
    In Russian
  - "U.S.S.R.-Philosophy" and "Report to the Commission on the Function of Philosophy in Liberal Education of The American Philosophical Association: Soviet Philosophy and Our Educational Opportunities,", undated (Folder 12: 9)
  - Lectures, Moscow, July 3 and 17, 1958 (Folder 12: 10)
  - Letters to the editor, clippings, 1961-1990 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Articles and essays relating to humanism, Marxism, and philosophy, 1970-1991 (Folder 12: 12)
  - Lectures, Korcula, Yugoslavia, July, 1963 (Folder 12: 13-14)
  - "Second Lecture", Korcula, Yugoslavia, July 4, 1963 (Folder 13: 1)
  - Articles on the subject of humanism, war and the first use of nuclear weapons, 1964-1989 (Folder 13: 2)
  - "The Future of Science and the Growing Role of the Ethical Factor" 1968, America's Unknown Atomic Soldier, undated (Folder 13: 3)
  - Letters to the editor, some regarding Alexander Haig, clippings, correspondence, 1968-1990 (Folder 13: 4-7)
  - Letters to the Editor, some regarding Alexander Haig, clippings, correspondence, 1970-1988 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Writings relating to Japan and nuclear omnicide, 1973-1979 (Folder 13: 9)
  - Catholic Bishops, articles and letters to the editor, 1981-1982 (Folder 13: 10)
  - Soviet "Criticism and Self-Criticism", undated (Folder 13: 11)
  - "USSR--Education: Aims and Objectives", undated (Folder 13: 12)
  - "Philosophy in Russia", undated (Folder 13: 13)
  - Lecture, undated (Folder 13: 14)
  - Notebooks, undated (Folder 13: 15)
- Subject File, 1935-1993 (Box 14-15)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, newsletters, clippings, articles, pamphlets, and other printed material, notes, transcripts, press releases, and miscellany.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Afghanistan, writings, clippings, program, 1979-1980 (Folder 14: 1)
  - Bulgaria, correspondence, SPSDM newsletter, clippings, 1973-1980 (Folder 14: 2)
  - California Initiative and No First Use (NFU) Campaign, 1978-1990 (Folder 14: 3)
  - Christian-Marxist Dialogue, clippings and correspondence, 1966-1985 (Folder 14: 4)
  - Clippings, correspondence, writings and notes, 1949-1977 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Columbia University Home Study Radio Broadcasts, transcripts, questionnaires, station lists, 1930 (Folder 14: 6)
  - Communism in the U.S. clippings, and a poll from the University Centers for Rational Alternatives signed by Sidney Hook, 1956-1971 (Folder 14: 7)
  - The Crisis, correspondence, programs, posters, 1979-1992 (Folder 14: 8)
  - Dialogues on the Philosophy of Marxism, reviews, 1974 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Domestic terrorism, clippings, 1963-1987 (Folder 14: 10)
  - The Enjoyment of Study, review, circa 1954 (Folder 14: 11)
  - Genocide, scientific humanism, social philosophy, first use of nuclear weapons, Marxism, pamphlets, 1949, 1968-1995. (Folder 14: 12)
    Some in German and Russian
  - Haig, Alexander, correspondence, including from Edward Kennedy, clippings, 1981 (Folder 14: 13)
  - "How Philosophy Is Studied in USSR" clipping, 1935 (Folder 14: 14)
  - Hubers, Paul, "Socialism & Omnicide", 1980s (Folder 14: 15)
  - International Philosophy Congress, XIII, Mexico City, one rolled panoramic photo of John Somerville and others, 1963 (Folder 14: 16)
  - International Philosophy Congress, XIII, Mexico City, one rolled panoramic photo of John Somerville and others, 1973-1993 (Folder 15: 1)
  - International Conference on General Semantics, August 9-13, 1965, San Francisco, clippings, photocopy (Folder 15: 2)
  - International relations, nuclear war and peace, articles and publications, 1978-1988 (Folder 15: 3)
  - IPPNO meeting minutes, report, correspondence, 1986-1988 (Folder 15: 4)
  - Japan, correspondence, clippings and writings, 1961-1979 (Folder 15: 5)
  - Japan, pamphlets and correspondence, mostly in Japanese, 1976-1980 (Folder 15: 6)
  - Kosing, Alfred, 1975 (Folder 15: 7)
  - "Mary Somerville," by A.W. Richeson, 1941 (Folder 15: 8)
  - "The Meaning of the Declaration of Independence: Philosophic Roots and Present Relevance," bibliographic notes relating to the article, undated (Folder 15: 9)
  - Molodtsov, V.S. "Philosophical Education in the U.S.S.R.,", undated (Folder 15: 10)
  - The Peace Revolution, reviews, clippings, correspondence, 1954-1988 (Folder 15: 11-12)
  - The Philosophy of Marxism, review, 1985 (Folder 15: 13)
  - The Philosophy of Peace, reviews, clippings, correspondence, 1949-1954 (Folder 15: 14)
  - Reviews, clippings, 1950-1954 (Folder 15: 15)
  - Soviet Marxism and Nuclear War, reviews, 1981-1983 (Folder 15: 16)
  - Soviet Philosophy, reviews, program, 1946-1948 (Folder 15: 17)
  - Soviet Philosophy, reviews, 1947-1948 (Folder 15: 18)
    Most in Danish
  - Somerville, John, images, Silhouette 1946, Hoover Tower steps 1949, Mexico City 1963, Tijuana 1985, St. Louis 1986, 1949-1986 (Folder 15: 19)
  - Theatre programs, 1936 (Folder 15: 20)
    In Danish